alright guys so just a little bit of
background as to what this the the
context of what I'm going to talk about
today because I suspect it's not like
anything you've seen before or probably
not in this context - well first is I
actually started my first company in
1998 and then took my last company
public in 2007 three different companies
so I had an opportunity to experience
the rise of the dot-com bubble the
decline of the dot-com bubble the the
death afterwards the rise of the 2006
frenzy the financial crisis all while
actually at the helm of a startup
company so the key message is macro
forces can impact your fate no matter
how good you are so we're gonna talk a
little bit about that from the top down
the second is that for some reason over
the past two decades I seem to have
gotten interested in things well in
advance of those things becoming
interesting to lots of other people it's
definitely harkens back to my nerd
beginnings but also a little bit of a
sort of an obsessive effort to
understand the sort of the nature of
reality at a fundamental level and then
logically things fall out of that that
seem obvious that they'll sort of emerge
in reality and then they do so I'm gonna
try to give you essentially my operating
model of what's going on in the world
and for some of you this may it could be
a complete waste of time and if so just
try to snore quietly for others this may
be really awesome so I'm hoping that
those folks get their money's worth
so what I'm to begin with is some
foundational assumptions try to sort of
get everybody on the same page about the
nature of how this big picture thing
called the world works the first is one
that I had to deal with a lot in the
early part of my career which is this
concept that history happens I remember
being in a meeting with the chairman of
EMI us when I was probably about 26 and
I tried to explain to him earnestly that
the music industry as he knew it was
already dead and the only choice he
really had was to figure out what his
new model is gonna look like and he sort
of glazed over and had no capacity to
can consider this right it wasn't that
even necessary that he didn't want to
but that the idea that the world that he
had grown up in could suddenly and a
a change wasn't part of his operating
model so the key idea here is that
history happens you know falls
apart big time absolutely anything that
currently exists will at some point no
longer exist
second this is the key idea by the way
if you get this slide you get a lot it
seems to happen all over the place
through something called punctuated
equilibrium all right s curves you see s
curves all the time and economics tremor
two curves disruption waves things like
that but frankly we see them all over
the place and we see them in the you
know the the breaking of dams the the
lightning bolt striking we see them in
population growth to see them all over
the place and the key message of an S
curve is this notion of it starts slow
most people have no idea it's happening
at all and frankly has very little
impact on the world and then at some
point for some reason it starts to
become more material and starts to
accelerate at this point it becomes the
hot new thing all right the new
revolution the new wave whatever happens
to be around here it is simply the new
thing it's the new standard it's what
happens then over at this point
it becomes the model that everybody
thinks is the nature of reality and it's
never going to change again up here it's
lost its innovative potential it becomes
extractive it just kind of goes along
for as long as it's relevant and
typically by the way tends to collapse
as the next one comes along alright so
think about these things in terms of
waves if it doesn't seem like anybody
really knows about what's going on but
you feel like it's super important you
might be over over here and then you
have to think okay where am I on this
curve if you're way over on the left of
the curve you're probably not gonna win
any time immediately as soon it'll take
a while there's gonna be a lot of forces
protected against you so you want to
take a strategy that takes that into
account if on the other hand things feel
like they're getting ready to pop then
you need a position for that as well
okay now these waves appear everywhere
in society and everywhere it means
everywhere right so whether you're
talking about fashion or education or
sexual activity family technology
finance money government every single
aspect of reality and particularly human
society proceeds by the evolution of
lots and lots of different waves that
feedback on each other and the
impact each other let's take for example
the rise of the miniskirt this was a
historical event but it was the
combination of let's see what I tracked
down I did the research significant
changes in textile manufacturing
technology an economic shift towards the
middle class post-war focus on youth and
youth culture the women's movement
changes in media and the emergence of
different kinds of new media all happens
simultaneously and they all overlapped
to cause this to happen and when this
happened it fed back on everything else
all rights what you get is an extremely
complex interference pattern multiple
different waves interacting with each
other ok so that's the background that's
the basic ideas some themes some
concepts the key point now is right now
several really really big waves are
converging and they're beginning to
become constructive interference they're
adding together I've just got a few here
there's many more right and that's the
but the key message is lots and they're
big globalization right somewhere around
1988 or so the expansion in the
inclusion of almost all of the world in
a single unified system hit and now it's
starting to feed back on itself write
the novel spaces where nobody goes and
nobody knows what's going on there
they're gone all right so we are now
post globalization we're beginning to
see what the world is like in a post
global world post-war capitalism in the
triumph of the West right everybody is
in some variation of the post-industrial
capitalist model right some flavor of it
ecosystem disruption right I don't know
how much how close do you track those
things but pick 15 different ecosystem
characteristics and almost all of them
are on the far end of the tipping point
on the curve population expansion we're
now looking at circumstances where the
total number of people on the planet are
also way beyond anything that we've ever
planned on before and any system that
was designed for a world that had say
four billion people in it which was you
know before 1960 probably is obsolete
right now because there's just more
people that it has to deal with the
maturity of a whole variety of different
cultural ideas that came out and hit the
West in the 1960s things like civil
rights the green movement excited
and then lastly the story of stuff that
gets talked about a lot here is
information technology and I'll probably
focus most on that because that's
relevant to a lot of the things that
happen entrepreneurially but the key
messages these things all line up and
that means for a very very big way and
very big waves have very big effects so
the proposition that I'm gonna make is
that we are already and have been for
some time in the middle of a crisis of
truly historical proportions right how
big I tend to think we're sort of in a
thousand year to 10,000 year equivalent
cycle I so think about the fall of Rome
right the complete collapse of Western
civilization to the Dark Ages or maybe
the emergence of civilization itself in
the Fertile Crescent 10,000 15,000 years
ago that's the level that we got to be
thinking about alright so if you're
thinking about things that happen
instead of 10 50 year cycles that's fine
but just be aware of the fact that the
wave may come right value faster than
you can imagine and I don't know where
you guys are from I happen to be from
Southern California so surfing waves is
one of the things that we do and it's
very fair to say that my primary
business acumen has been finding waves
spotted them and paddling into them I'm
usually very early so other guys end up
getting sort of all the all the big wins
but it's kind of fun alright so what
we're looking at then is a comprehensive
global in scale civilization level
collapse and what I mean by civilization
is civilization is the complete toolkit
all the sets of institutions concepts
processes models behaviors that we have
enculturated ourselves into to do all
the things that we need to do as humans
might the way we feed ourselves the way
we groom ourselves when we find mates
all that kind of stuff
and it's comprehensive its global all
across because everything's now
entrained and they're all been being
rendered obsolete either because the
world has changed more rapid than they
can handle or because they themselves
have become dysfunctional I'm not going
to go into too much depth on that and
these sorts of things always happen in
the same way right they started to weak
and go towards the center in this case
they're starting at the edge and working
towards the core so briefly things at
the edge
I remember when journalism was mostly
newspapers in television that's the edge
that was a very weak spot in the
existing legacy system and went digital
very quickly
journalism largely has already gone
through the transition and most
journalism now happens in a way that
would have made Cronkite have no idea
what's going on right
by contrast harder things are at the
core these things are gonna take longer
and they're at the the last things to
disrupt and as they disrupt the
consequences are more significant all
right so one money money turns out to
have been a fundamental component of the
major legacy institutions that are part
of our current temporary global
civilization and not just the form of
money the institution is around it the
way we use it we use it to decide and
make coordinate behavior and as we know
certainly everybody here knows I saw the
sign out front money is now well into
the disruptive wave right maybe the
early majority level most people around
the world are now beginning to be aware
the fact that money is not magic it
didn't come from God people make it and
people can change it right that's a
pretty significant psychological change
from where it was 20 years ago
governance and I was here actually why I
got invited to this talk talking about
the fact that governance is just really
entering into the disruption way and the
governance is like how we collectively
make decisions about the Worr sorts of
things that we do whether that's in a
corporation and corporate governance in
the way that we make decisions or at an
organizational level or big-picture
governance like you know the I will say
right now on record that within 50 years
the nation state as a fundamental unit
of global political power will be
subordinate it won't go away completely
but there will be other forces that will
be more important in deciding the
allocation of resources and the move
into people at a global level and then
the last is fundamental operating models
this is more abstract deeper stuff you
have to read things like Foucault and
Judah Louise to kind of get a better
sense of it but these are the the ways
the toolkits that we have for going out
and getting things done so for example
in the contemporary environment after
World War Two kind of the Six Sigma
bureaucratic hierarchy is an operating
model it's how you can get things done
we got pretty good at it right it put us
on the moon and built the interstate
highway system this stuff is getting
thrown out all the way and some
significant things around completely
deconstructing the model of even like
the corporation is almost certainly on
the horizon
in fact again I'd go ahead and predict
that the form of corporation that we've
seen for the past hundred years is
almost certainly on its way out and
probably in the next 20 years so that's
big stuff right those are major
disruptions the key message is not only
they big but as they disrupt starting at
the outside and working their way in
they bring widths and lots and lots and
lots of other stuff so think for example
you guys are familiar the TPP the
trans-pacific partnership it's sort of a
international law on trade so in many
ways I mean it's a big trade but in many
ways certain chunks of it started all
the way back in 1997 when I was getting
involved in the mp3 movement because the
mp3 movement was hitting a very weak
spot which was the music industry they
were very very weak right very easy for
them to be disrupted in fact they were
disrupted almost instantaneously except
for one thing they all had really strong
relationships with governance the the
music industry had very tight
relationships with legislature with with
judges and so that's what they held on
to and what they did is that pull all
the destructive energy that was pointing
at the music industry at a market level
and put that energy onto the legislative
level and they've been fighting the
copyright battles ever since for the
past decade and a half and other guys
have gotten into it as their business
models have been threatened and a big
chunk of the TPP is in fact a leveling
up of governance playing the game of
defending older models okay
and as governance itself then is put on
the table and as it begins to be
disrupted giant chunks of the world
begin to change relatively rapidly you
know the blockchain stuff is blowing
people's minds they've already been
engaged in several conversations with
folks who are offering the idea of
jurisdiction innovation I go to some
local jurisdiction but sovereign nation
they will modify their laws to optimize
for particular business models that are
not legal in other kinds of nation
states that the blockchain can really
take great advantage of and you can
think of thousands actually even just a
few seconds and what is the
international legal structure do with
that it's really hard to say it but it's
gonna be interesting and disruptive but
here's the thing if I'm right and we're
actually going in through a level of a
thousand ten thousand year disruption it
goes even deeper than that the the
physical layer of the institutional
structures that we use to do
things like the way we do governance the
way we do business is kind of like the
candy coating on the outside or the
things we actually need to have done so
this is a map of what the core really
looks like you've got things like
politics art medicine you're the kind of
general categories of what human beings
need to have done and inside that are
actually the deep human needs that every
that emerged that these things emerge
from like the need for identity they
need to deal with the fact that you're
gonna die the need to have ideas and
creativity right these are the core
things that you know unless the
transhumanist stuff really takes off
these are probably not going to change
in this way so we'll end up happening is
that new things are going to clothe them
and this is like the core this is the
source of raw energy people need to have
these things satisfied and as old models
go away these ma these things need to be
satisfied so new models build up around
them and they build up around them in
very complex fashion you take a look at
your history about how these things have
happened in the past you know certain
and sometimes things like medicine and
religion are part of the same structure
and sometimes they'll break apart and
they'll be very different sometimes
family and law are the same structure
right so at the core what I think right
now is that we could be looking at three
big ones one is identity you know who
are you
what does it mean to be you what does it
mean to be understood in relationship to
other kinds of identities the second is
sense making how do you make sense of
the world what the hell is going on and
how do I behave in this environment and
the third is meaning and what is
actually important what is meaningful
where are places where I ought to where
I should put my energy in my focus those
answers those things those questions
have really easy simple answers in
mature coherent cultures right now
they're falling apart like crazy and
they're going to fall apart faster as
the old legacy answers are shown to be
in the middle of disruption